<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and exact relation of the severall informations, examinations, and confessions of the late witches, arraigned and executed in the county of Essex. Who were arraigned and condemned at the late sessions, holden at Chelmesford before the Right Honorable Robert, Earle of Warwicke, and severall of his Majesties justices of peace, the 29 of July, 1645. Wherein the severall murthers, and devillish witchcrafts, committed on the bodies of men, women, and children, and divers cattell, are fully discovered. Published by authoritie.</title>
            <author>H. F.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85006</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E296_35</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200218</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861023</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861023</idno>
            <idno type="VID">130529</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85006)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 130529)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 49:E296[35])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and exact relation of the severall informations, examinations, and confessions of the late witches, arraigned and executed in the county of Essex. Who were arraigned and condemned at the late sessions, holden at Chelmesford before the Right Honorable Robert, Earle of Warwicke, and severall of his Majesties justices of peace, the 29 of July, 1645. Wherein the severall murthers, and devillish witchcrafts, committed on the bodies of men, women, and children, and divers cattell, are fully discovered. Published by authoritie.</title>
                  <author>H. F.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. for Henry Overton, and Benj. Allen, and are to be sold at their shops in Popes-head Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The preface is signed: H.F.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 19".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trials (Witchcraft) --  England --  Chelmsford --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Witchcraft --  England --  Essex --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Chelmsford (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:130529:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A true and exact RELATION Of the ſeverall Informations, Examinations, and Confeſſions of the late Witches, arraigned and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted in the County of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who were arraigned and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at the late Seſſions, holden at <hi>Chelmesford</hi> before the Right Honorable ROBERT, Earle of <hi>Warwicke,</hi> and ſeverall of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Juſtices of Peace, the 29 of <hi>July,</hi> 1645.</p>
            <p>Wherein the ſeverall murthers, and devilliſh Witchcrafts, committed on the bodies of men, women, and children, and divers cattell, are fully diſcovered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Henry Overton,</hi> and <hi>Benj. Allen,</hi> and are to be ſold at their Shops in <hi>Popes-head Alley.</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:130529:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:130529:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>INGENUOUS READER;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou haſt here preſented to thee a ſad Emblem of the ſtrange ſleights and cunning ſubtilties, whereby Satan la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours daily to inſnare ſoules, and at laſt to bring them to utter ruine; who being that grand impoſtor, ſoone began this worke, even in the morning of the Creation, in the body of a Serpent miraculouſly, to reaſon, diſpute, ſpeake, and conferre with <hi>Evah;</hi> and never ceaſed till he had laid the honour of thoſe glorious creatures in the duſt: and therefore is called that <hi>old Serpent,</hi> that decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth all the world, by whoſe deceitfull promiſes and ſubtill devices (for his own end, and deſire of their deſtruction,) hath inſnared and drawne theſe poore ſilly creatures, into theſe horrid and deteſtable practiſes, of renouncing God and Chriſt, and entring into a ſolemne league and contract with the Devill
<note n="a" place="margin">As one them witne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed in open Court, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca VVeſt</hi>
               </note>; the thought whereof is ſufficient to cauſe a man to be filled with horror and aſtoniſhment. The Law and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe command of God doth allow of no familiarity or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry of any other ſpirit, but from himſelfe; as <hi>Iſa. 8.19. And when they ſhall ſay unto you, ſeeke unto them that have familiar ſpirits, and unto Wizards, that peep and that mutter, ſhould not a people ſeeke unto their God, &amp;c.</hi> Vnder this interrogative is underſtood this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative,
<pb facs="tcp:130529:3"/>A people ſhould inquire of no other ſpirit, but of their God onely. By which alſo it is evident, that all ſpirits that doe ſuffer themſelves to be inquired at, are evill ſpirits, and therefore
<note n="b" place="margin">Angeli boni non poſſunt peccare confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiper grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, Angeli mali per mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam obſtinati non poſſunt benè velle.</note> Devills. And though theſe devilliſh pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes were frequent and common amongst heathens and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidells, who uſually held familiarity with theſe ſpirits, and many inquired of them in their Oracles; and therefore cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thoſe ſpirits that gave anſwer by them, <hi>Daemons</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>q d.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ex</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>diſco ſcio, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vido. Vide</hi> Lexic. Paſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, 157.</note> of their skill and knowledge in ſoretelling things to come: yet now when the light of the Goſpel ſhineth ſo gloriouſly, that ſuch a generation of poore deluded ſoules (and to ſuch a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as hath of late been diſcovered) ſhould be found amongst us, is much more matter of admiration and aſtoniſhment
<note n="d" place="margin">See Deut. 8.14, 15.</note>. I doubt not but theſe things may ſeeme as incredible unto ſome, as they are matter of admiration unto others. <hi>Nolle nimis ſapere,</hi> ſaith the Poet, It is true wiſdome not to be too wiſe; that is, not to know nor deſire to know more then is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed or needfull; needfull not in our deſires, but in Gods decree: Here then let reaſonable men be perſwaded not too much (as is uſuall) to ſwell with indignation, or to be puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed with impatience, where God doth not apertly reveale and plainly (as they deſire and thinke needfull) the ſubtile Engines and myſticall craft of the Devill in the machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Witches</hi> and <hi>Sorcerers;</hi> but ſoberly, modeſtly, and diſcreetly, ſo far forth-be contented to purſue the triall and juſt way of their diſcoverie, as with ſenſe, with reaſon, with Religion, is juſt and righteous; knowing, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is beyond theſe liſts, is reaſonleſſe, ſenſleſſe and impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. The greateſt doubt and queſtion will be, whether it be in the power of the <hi>Devill</hi> to perform ſuch aſportation and locall tranſlation of the bodies of <hi>Witches;</hi> it ſeemeth in reaſon a thing whereunto the <hi>Devill</hi> is unable: And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe ſupernaturall works, which are above the power of
<pb facs="tcp:130529:3"/>man to do, and proper only to Spirits, whether they are reall, or only imaginary and fained. In anſwer to which, it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry probable that the <hi>Devill</hi> hath power to diſpoſe and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the bodies of men and women, where God himſelf doth not countermand or prohibit: as inſtance, when hee took the body of our Saviour and ſet it upon a pinacle of the Temple; and theſe ſupernaturall acts may appear to the outward ſenſe, as Hiſtories; and many other true reports and Records of other wonderfull works and ſupernaturall feats, all alike of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to the outward ſenſe. It is true, that a Spirit, and a ſpirituall work ſimply in it ſelf, in the own nature and ſubſtance cannot be ſeen by any bodily eye, or be deprehended by any outward ſenſe, notwithſtanding, as they do mix them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with bodily ſubſtances, are certainly tried and ſubject to the ſenſe: For illuſtration hereof, inſtance may be given in holy Scripture, as the <hi>Sorcerers</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> where water was turned into blood, the rod into a Serpent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall power their eyes did maniſeſtly ſee the water, and as apparently after ſee the blood, and the rod turned into a Serpent, the eye being a true and undeceived witneſſe of both: Things imagined and fancied, are eaſily diſcerned from thoſe things that are reall and true objects. But it may be demanded, whether a Spirit or <hi>Devill</hi> can cauſe ſuch a tranſmutation of the bodies of <hi>Witches</hi> into thoſe ſeverall ſhapes and forms of Cats, Dogges, Birds, and other creatures, as is often reported, where <hi>Witches</hi> and <hi>Sorcerers</hi> have lived. The anſwer is, that it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in nature, and in the ordinary unchangeable courſe of all things created by God, that one individuall and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſubſtance or entire thing ſhould be wholly divided from it ſelf, and yet be it ſelf;
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Diabolus Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aemulus, quo ſe fallaci ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine inſinuet in animos ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icium:</hi> Calv. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Inſtit. cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</note> for there can be no reall or true tranſmutation of one ſubſtance, or nature into another, but either by creation or generation. Now creation is the
<pb facs="tcp:130529:4"/>worke of in infinite power, and therefore of God alone. The <hi>Devill</hi> then cannot create, neither can he do it by any courſe of true generation,
<note n="f" place="margin">Naturaeſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaria Dei poteſtas.</note> becauſe a true and reall generation hath many precedent alterations, and by little and little, in ſpace of time
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Generatio non eſt niſi in tempore id<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> apparata ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teria per ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsionem mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationis,</hi> &amp;c. Scal. <hi>de ſubt. exercit.</hi> Sect. 6</note> growes unto the perjection of that kind unto which it doth tend, or is begotten; therefore they are but ſeeming and jugling tranſmutations of the <hi>Devill:</hi> And here that ſaying of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> may be alledged, <hi>De civit. Dei, lib. 18. cap. 18. (Nec ſane Daemones natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras creant, ſed ſpecie tenus, quae à Deo creata ſunt commutant, ut videantur eſſe quae non ſunt)</hi> that is, Devils cannot create any nature or ſubſtance, but in jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling ſhew, or ſeemingly only, whereby with falſe ſhadowes covering thoſe things which are created of God to cauſe them to ſeem that which they are not indeed. Take one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the jugglings and illuſions ef the <hi>Devill</hi> above all the reſt, which doth moſt palpably detect him herein, is a Hiſtory related by <hi>Johannes Baptiſta Porta,</hi> in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond book, <hi>de Magia naturali;</hi> hee there witneſſeth, that upon the <hi>Devils</hi> ſuggeſtion, a <hi>Witch</hi> believed firmly and perſwaded her ſelf, that all the night ſhee had rid in the aire, over divers great mountaines, and met in conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles with other <hi>Witches,</hi> when the ſame night, the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Author himſelf, with others that watched her and ſaw her all that imagined time of her tranſvection in the aire, to be within her chamber profoundly ſleeping; yea, had ſmitten her, made her fleſh blew with ſtrokes, and could not awake her, nor perſwade her afterward when ſhe was awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked that they had ſo uſed her, or at all had ſeene or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held her; thus prevalent was the juggling power of the <hi>Devill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many other like inſtances of like nature might be added, only what here is publiſhed and communicated unto the
<pb facs="tcp:130529:4"/>world, may ſufficiently diſcover thoſe ſtrong deluſions which theſe poor ſoules were given up unto, who now according to their demerits, and according to the Lawes of God and this kingdome eſtabliſhed, have received their juſt reward.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="statement">
            <pb facs="tcp:130529:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:130529:5"/>
            <head>THE INFORMATION of <hi>John Rivet</hi> of <hi>Mannintree,</hi> Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, taken before Sir <hi>Harbottell Grimſton,</hi> Knight and Baronet, one of the Members of the Honourable Houſe of Commons:</head>
            <head type="sub">And Sir <hi>Thomas Bowes,</hi> Knight, another of his Majeſties Juſtices of Peace for this <hi>County, the</hi> 21<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>of March.</hi> 1645.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Informant ſaith, That about <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> laſt, his wife was taken ſicke, and lame, with ſuch violent fits, that this Informant verily conceived her ſickneſſe was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then meerly naturall: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon this Informant about a fortnight ſince went to a Cunning Woman, the wife of one <hi>Hovye</hi> at <hi>Hadleigh</hi> in <hi>Suffolke,</hi> who told this Informant, that his wife was curſed by two women who were neere neighbours to this Informant, the one dwelling a little above his houſe, and the other beneath his houſe, this Informants houſe ſtanding on the ſide of an Hill: Whereupon he beleeved his ſaid wife was bewitched by one <hi>Elizabeth Clarke,</hi> alias <hi>Bedingfield,</hi> that dwelt above this Informants houſe, for that the ſaid <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> mother and ſome other of her kinsfolke did ſuffer death for Witchcraft and murther.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:130529:6"/>
            <head>The Information of <hi>Matthew Honkins,</hi> of <hi>Mannintree,</hi> Gent. <hi>taken upon Oath before us the</hi> 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>day of</hi> March. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, That the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Clarke</hi> (ſuſpected for a Witch as aforeſaid) being by the appointment of the ſaid Juſtices watched certaine nights, for the better diſcovery of her wicked Practiſes, this Informant came into the roome where the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was watched; as aforeſaid, the laſt night, being the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of this inſtant <hi>March,</hi> but intended not to have ſtayed long there. But the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> forth with told this Informant and one Maſter <hi>Sterne</hi> there preſent, if they would ſtay and do the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> no hurt, ſhee would call one of her white Impes, and play with it in her lap; but this Informant told her, they would not allow of it; And that ſtaying there a while longer, the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> confeſſed ſhee had had carnall copulation with the Devill ſix or ſeven yeares; and that he would appeare to her three or foure times in a weeke at her bed ſide, and goe to bed to her, and lye with her halfe a night together in the ſhape of a proper Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, with a laced band, having the whole proportion of a man, and would ſay to her, <hi>Beſſe Imuſt lye with you,</hi> and ſhee did never deny him: And within a quarter of an houre after there appeared an Impe like to a Dog, which was white, with ſome ſandy ſpots, and ſeemed to be very fat and plumpe; with very ſhort legges, who forthwith vaniſhed away: And the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſaid the name of that Impe was, <hi>Jarmara:</hi> And immediately there appeared ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Impe, which ſhee called <hi>Vinegar Tom,</hi> in the ſhape of a Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound with long legges: And the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> then ſaid that the next Impe ſhould be a black Impe, and ſhould come for the ſaid Maſter <hi>Sterne,</hi> which appeared, but preſently vaniſhed: And the laſt that appeared was in the ſhape of a Polcat, but the head ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what bigger. And the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> then told this Informant that ſhee had five Impes of her owne, and two of the Impes of the old Beldam <hi>Weſte</hi> (meaning one <hi>Anne Weſte,</hi> widow) who is now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſuſpected to be guilty of Witchcraft: And ſaid ſometimes the Impes of the old Beldam ſucked on the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times her Impes ſucked on the old Beldam <hi>Weſte.</hi> And the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> further told this Informant, that Satan would never let
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:130529:6"/>her reſt, or be quiet, untill ſhee did conſent to the killing of the Hogges of one M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Edwards</hi> of <hi>Mannintree</hi> aforeſaid, and the Horſe of one <hi>Robert Tayler</hi> of the ſame Towne: And this Informant fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, That going from the Houſe of the ſaid M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Edwards</hi> to his own Houſe about nine or ten of the Clock that night, with his Greyhound with him, he ſaw the Greyhound ſuddenly give a jumpe, and ran as ſhee had been in a full courſe after an Hare; And that when this Informant made haſte to ſee what his Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound ſo eagerly purſued; He eſpied a white thing about the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a Kitlyn, and the Greyhound ſtanding alooſe from it; and that by and by the ſaid white Impe or Kitlyn daunced about the ſaid Greyhound, and by all likelihood bit off a piece of the fleſh of the ſhoulder of the Greyhound; for the Greyhound came ſhrieking and crying to this Informant with a piece of fleſh torne from her ſhoulder. And this Informant further ſaith, That com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into his own Yard that night, he eſpied a black thing, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned like a Cat, onely it was thrice as big, ſitting on a ſtraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berry-bed, and fixing the eyes on this Informant; and when he went towards it, it leaped over the pale towards this Informant, as he thought, but ran quite through the Yard, with his Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound after it to a great Gate, which was underſet with a paire of Tumbrell Strings, and did throw the ſaid Gate wide open, and then vaniſhed; And the ſaid Greyhound returned againe to this Informant, ſhaking and trembling exceedingly.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>John Sterne,</hi> Gent. taken <hi>upon Oath before us the</hi> 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>day of March.</hi> 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, That watching with <hi>Elizabeth Clarke,</hi> (ſuſpected for Witchcraft, as aforeſaid) ſhee confeſſed that the Devill had had carnall copulation with her in the likeneſſe of a man; and that the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> deſired this Informant, and the reſt that were in the roome with her to ſit downe, and ſaid, ſhee would ſhew this Informant and the reſt ſome of her Impes: And within halfe an houre there appeared a white thing in the likeneſs of a Cat, but not altogether ſo big: And being asked if ſhe would not be afraid of her Impes; the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> anſwered; <hi>What
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:130529:7"/>doe yee thinke I am afraid of my children?</hi> And that ſhee called the name of that white Impe, <hi>Hoult.</hi> And this Informant further ſaith, That preſently after there appeared another white Impe, with red ſpots, as big as a ſmall dog, which ſhee then called <hi>Jarmara:</hi> And that immediately after, there appeared at the threſhold of the doore another Impe about the bigneſſe of the firſt, but did preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vaniſh away. And then the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> being asked if any more Impes would come; ſhee anſwered, <hi>That Vinegar Tom would come by and by.</hi> And forthwith there appeared another in the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a dumb Dogge, ſomewhat bigger then any of the former: And the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> alſo told this Informant, That ſhee had three Impes from her mother, which were of a browne colour, and two from the old Beldam <hi>Weſte:</hi> And that there had five Impes appeared; But ſhee had one more called <hi>Sack and Sugar,</hi> which had been hard at worke, and it would be long before it came, but it ſhould teare this Informant. And a while after the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſaid, That it was well for this Informant he was ſo quick, otherwiſe the ſaid Impe had ſoone skipped upon his face, and perchance had got into his throate, and then there would have been a feaſt of Toades in this Informants belly. And the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> further confeſſed to this Informant, that ſhee had one Impe for which ſhee would fight up to the knees in bloud, before ſhee would loſe it. And that her Impes did commonly ſuck on the old Beldam <hi>Weſte;</hi> and that the ſaid old Beldams Impes, did ſuck on her the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> likewiſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Frances Milles, Grace Norman, Mary Phillips,</hi> and <hi>Mary Parſley,</hi> taken upon oath before <hi>the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>of March. An. Dom.</hi> 1645.</head>
            <p>THeſe Informants ſay joyntly, That watching with the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Clarke,</hi> ſuſpected as aforeſaid, about twelve of the Clock laſt night, the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſmacked with her mouth, and beckned with her hand, and inſtantly there appeared a white thing about the bigneſſe of a Cat; and that theſe Informants ſaw five Impes more, which the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> named as aforeſaid. And that the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> told theſe Informants, That the old
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:130529:7"/>Beldam (meaning the ſaid <hi>Anne Weſte</hi>) did by Witchcraft kill the wife of one <hi>Robert Oakes</hi> of <hi>Lawford</hi> in the County aforeſaid; and was the death of a Clothiers childe of <hi>Dedham</hi> in the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Eſſex:</hi> both which dyed as theſe Informants very well know about a weeke ſince. And the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> told theſe Informants, that the ſaid old Beldam <hi>Weſte</hi> had the wife of one <hi>William Cole</hi> of <hi>Mannintree</hi> aforeſaid in handling, who dyed not long ſince of a pining and languiſhing diſeaſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>George Turner</hi> taken upon oath <hi>the</hi> 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>day of March.</hi> 1645. <hi>before the ſaid Juſtices.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, That going to the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Clarke,</hi> alias <hi>Bedingfeild,</hi> after ſhee was apprehended, and asking her whether ſhee had any hand in the drowning of one <hi>Thomas Turner,</hi> this Informants Brother, who was caſt away at Sea about thirty moneths ſince; the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> anſwered, That the old Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>Weſte</hi> raiſed that winde that ſunke his Hoy: And that ſhe the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had no hand in that buſineſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>John Bankes</hi> of <hi>Mannintree</hi> taken <hi>upon oath before the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>of March.</hi> 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, That watching with the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> he doth informe and confirme all the particulars expreſſed and ſet downe in the Information of the ſaid M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Sterne.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Edward Parſley</hi> of <hi>Mannintree, taken upon oath before the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>of March.</hi> 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, That watching with the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Clarke,</hi> alias <hi>Bedingfeild,</hi> the laſt night, he asked the ſaid <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> if he ſhould continue ſtill in the roome with her; And the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> deſired he ſhould, if he would fight for her with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills, for they would come this night, and that which ſhee called
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:130529:8"/>
               <hi>Hoult</hi> would come firſt, and then that which ſhee called <hi>Jarmara;</hi> which did appeare in the likeneſſe of a white Dogge, with red ſpots; and preſently after there appeared that Impe which ſhee called <hi>Vinegar Tom;</hi> and then that which ſhee called <hi>Sack and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar:</hi> And the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> then told this Informant, that the Devill had had poſſeſſion of her ſix or ſeven yeares. And that he had oftentimes knocked at her dore in the night time; and that ſhee did ariſe, open the dore and let him in; and that he went to bed to her three or foure times in a weeke, and had the carnall knowledge of her as a man.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Examination of the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Clarke,</hi> alias Bedingfeild, <hi>taken before the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>of March.</hi> 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant ſaith,
<note place="margin">Executed at <hi>Chelmesford.</hi>
               </note> That about ſix moneths ſince ſhee met with the ſaid <hi>Anne Weſte,</hi> widow, (who is now likewiſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended) in a field neere the houſe of the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> where the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was picking up a few ſticks; The ſaid <hi>Anne Weſte</hi> ſeemed much to pitie this Examinant for her lameneſſe (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving but one leg) and her poverty; And ſaid to this Examinant, That there was wayes and meanes for her to live much better then now ſhee did: And ſaid, that ſhee would ſend to this Examinant a thing like a little Kitlyn, which would fetch home ſome victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls for this Examinant; and that it ſhould doe her no hurt. And this Examinant ſaith, that within two or three nights after there came a white thing to her in the night, and the night after a gray one, which ſpake to this Examinant, and told her they would doe her no hurt, but would helpe her to an Husband, who ſhould maintaine her ever after: And that theſe two things came into this Examinants bed every night, or every other night, and ſucked upon the lower parts of her body.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Robert Tayler</hi> of <hi>Mannintree,</hi> taken <hi>upon oath before the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 23<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>day of Aprill.</hi> 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, That about nine weekes ſince, <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the wife of <hi>Edward Gooding</hi> (who is accuſed by the ſaid <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Clarke</hi> to be a confederate with her) came to the Shop of this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:130529:8"/>Informant, and deſired to be truſted for half a pound of Cheeſe, which being denyed, ſhee went away, muttering and mumbling to her ſelf, and within a few houres came again with money, and bought a pound of Cheeſe of this Informant, and the ſame night this Informant having an Horſe ſtanding in his ſtable, the ſaid Horſe was taken in a ſtrange manner ſick and lame; whereupon this Informant ſent for four Farriers to have their beſt advice, who could not diſcover the cauſe of the diſeaſe; but the ſaid Horſe about four dayes after died: And this Informant alſo ſaith, that it was obſerved by himſelf, and divers others, who often went to ſee the ſaid Horſe, that ſtill upon their coming into the ſtable, he lay quiet, and looked cheerfully, but as ſoon as the door was ſhut, and the Horſe alone, hee did violently beat himſelf, and that the belly of the ſaid Horſe would rumble and make a noyſe, as a foule chimney ſet on fire: And this Informant further ſaith, that hee is induced to believe, that the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Gooding</hi> was the cauſe of the death of his ſaid Horſe; for that this Informant hath heard, that <hi>Elizabeth Clark,</hi> and <hi>Anne Leech</hi> widow, (who ſtand both accuſed for Witchcraft, and have confeſſed themſelves guilty) have impeached the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Gooding</hi> for killing of this ſaid Horſe, and that the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Gooding</hi> is a lewd woman, and to this Informants knowledge, hath kept company with the ſaid <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Clark, Anne Leech,</hi> and <hi>Anne Weſt,</hi> which <hi>Anne Weſt</hi> hath been ſuſpected for a Witch many yeers ſince, and ſuffered impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment for the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Elizabeth Gooding,</hi> taken before <hi>the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>of</hi> April, 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant ſaith,
<note place="margin">Executed at <hi>Chelmesford.</hi>
               </note> that ſhee is not guilty of any one parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular charged upon her in the Information of the ſaid <hi>Robert Tailer.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Richard Edwards</hi> of <hi>Mannintree aforeſaid, taken before the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 23. <hi>day of</hi> April, 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, That about twelve moneths ſince, upon a Sabbath day, after the afternoon Sermon, driving his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:130529:9"/>Cowes home by the houſe of <hi>Anne Leech</hi> of <hi>Miſley</hi> widow, about forty yards from her ſaid houſe, a black Cowe of this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mants, (being very well to his thinking) fell down, and within two dayes after died. And the very next day driving his Cowes from the ſame paſture, this Informant had a white Cowe that fell down within a Rod of the ſame place, where the other Cowe fell, (being alſo, as this Informant conceived, ſound and well) and within a weak after dyed; and hee further ſaith, that hee cauſed both the ſaid Cowes to be opened, and that there could be no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe diſcovered, which might occaſion their death: And this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant likewiſe ſaith, that about <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, hee had a childe nurſed by one Goodwife <hi>Wyles,</hi> dwelling neer the houſes of the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Clark</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth Gooding,</hi> and that his ſaid childe was taken ſick, and had very ſtrange fits, extending the limbs, and rowling the eyes, and within two dayes after dyed: And this Informant doth verily believe, that <hi>Anne Leech,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth Gooding,</hi> were the death of his ſaid child, as is confeſſed by the ſaid <hi>Anne Leech</hi> in her own Confeſſion and Examination.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Anne Leech</hi> of <hi>Miſley</hi> in the <hi>County aforeſaid, widow, taken before the ſaid Juſtices,</hi> April 14. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant ſaith,
<note place="margin">Executed at <hi>Chelmesford.</hi>
               </note> That ſhe had a grey Impeſent to her, and that this Examinant, together with the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Clark,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the wife of <hi>Edward Gooding,</hi> did about a yeer ſince, ſend their Imps to kill a black Cowe and a white Cowe of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Edwards,</hi> which was done accordingly: And this Examinant ſaith, that ſhe ſent her gray Imp, <hi>Elizabeth Clark</hi> a black Imp, and <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Gooding</hi> a white Imp: And this Examinant ſaith, that about thirty yeeres ſince, ſhee ſent a gray Imp to kill two Horſes of one M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Bragge</hi> of <hi>Miſley,</hi> which were killed accordingly; and that the occaſion of her malice was, becauſe Miſtreſſe <hi>Bragge</hi> had told this Examinant, that ſhee ſuſpected her to be a naughty woman; and this Examinant confeſſeth, that ſhe and the ſaid <hi>Eliz. Gooding,</hi> ſent either of them an Imp to deſtroy the childe of the ſaid M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Edwards;</hi> this Examinants Imp being then a white one, and <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth Goodings</hi> a black Imp; and that about thirty yeers ſince,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:130529:9"/>this Examinant had the ſaid white Imp, and two others, a gray, and a black Imp of one <hi>Anne,</hi> the wife of <hi>Robert Pearce</hi> of <hi>Stoak</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> being her brother; and that theſe Imps went com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly from one to another, and did miſchief where ever they went; and that when this Examinant did not ſend and imploy them abroad to do miſchief, ſhe had not her health, but when they were imployed, ſhe was healthfull and well, and that theſe Imps did uſually ſuck thoſe teats which were found about the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie parts of her body; and that the ſaid Imps did often ſpeak to this Examinant, and told her, ſhe ſhould never feele hell torments, and that they ſpake to her in an hollow voyce, which ſhe plainly underſtood: And this Examinant alſo confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, that ſhe ſent her gray Imp to <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Kirk</hi> of <hi>Mannyntree,</hi> about three yeers ſince, to deſtroy her; and upon the ſending of the ſaid Imp, the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſpace of one whole yeer, untill ſhee dyed, and that the occaſion of offence this Examinant took againſt her the ſaid <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> was, for that ſhe had asked a Coife of the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which ſhee refuſed to give to this Examinant. And further, this Examinant ſaith, that long ſince, but the exact time ſhe cannot remember, ſhe ſent her gray Imp to kill the daughter of the widow <hi>Rawlyns</hi> of <hi>Miſley</hi> aforeſaid; and the reaſon was, becauſe this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminant was put out of her Farm, and the ſaid widow <hi>Rawlyns</hi> put in, where ſhee dwelleth at this preſent. And moreover, this Examinant confeſſeth, that ſhe was acquainted with the ſending of an Imp by the aforeſaid <hi>Elizabeth Gooding,</hi> to vex and torment <hi>Mary</hi> the wife of <hi>John Tayler</hi> of <hi>Mannyntree</hi> aforeſaid about three yeers ſince; and this Examinant being asked why ſhe did not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it to the ſaid <hi>Mary,</hi> ſhe ſald, the Devill would not ſuffer her, and that the cauſe of the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Goodings</hi> malice againſt the ſaid <hi>Mary</hi> was, becauſe the ſaid <hi>Mary</hi> refuſed to give to the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſome Beeregood. And laſtly, this Examinant ſaith, that about eight weeks ſince, this Examinant, the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Gooding,</hi> and one <hi>Anne Weſt</hi> of <hi>Lawford</hi> widow, met together at the houſe of the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Clark,</hi> where there was a book read, wherein ſhee thinks there was no goodneſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:130529:10"/>
            <head>The Information of <hi>Grace</hi> the wife of <hi>Richard Glaſcock of</hi> Mannyntree, <hi>taken upon oath before the ſaid Juſtices, the</hi> 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day <hi>of</hi> April, 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, that there being ſome falling out between <hi>Mary</hi> the wife of <hi>Edward Parſley</hi> of <hi>Mannyntree,</hi> and one <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Clark,</hi> the wife of <hi>Thomas Clark</hi> (which ſaid <hi>Hellen</hi> is the daughter of the ſaid <hi>Anne Leech,</hi> whoſe confeſſion doth imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately precede) this Informant heard the ſaid <hi>Hellen</hi> to ſay, as the ſaid <hi>Hellen</hi> paſſed by this Informants door in the ſtreet, that <hi>Mary</hi> the daughter of the ſaid <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>Mary Parſley</hi> ſhould rue for all, whereupon, preſently the ſaid <hi>Mary</hi> the daughter, fell ſick, and died within ſix weeks after.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Edward Parſley</hi> of <hi>Mannyntree, taken upon oath before the ſaid Juſtices,</hi> April 11. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, that his ſaid daughter ſickned very ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, as the ſaid <hi>Grace Glaſcock</hi> hath before informed, and died about ſix weeks ſince; and this Informant doth verily believe, the ſaid <hi>Hellen Clark</hi> was the death of his ſaid daughter.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Hellen Clark,</hi> taken before <hi>the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>of</hi> April, 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant confeſſeth,
<note place="margin">Executed at <hi>Mannyntree.</hi>
               </note> that about ſix weeks ſince, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill appeared to her in her houſe, in the likeneſſe of a white Dog, and that ſhe calleth that Familiar <hi>Elimanzer;</hi> and that this Examinant hath often fed him with milk-pottage; and that the ſaid Familiar ſpake to this Examinant audibly, and bade her deny Chriſt, and ſhee ſhould never want, which ſhee did then aſſent unto, but doth altogether deny the killing of the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſaid <hi>Edward Parſley.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:130529:10"/>
            <head>The Information of <hi>Prudence Hart,</hi> the wife of <hi>Thomas Hart of</hi> Lawford, <hi>taken upon oath before us the</hi> 23. <hi>of</hi> Aprill, 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, that about eight week ſince, being at her Pariſh Church, on the Sabbath day, half a mile diſtant from her houſe, and being about twenty weeks gone with childe, and to her thinking, very well and healthfull, upon the ſudden ſhee was taken with great pains, and miſcarried before ſhee could be got home; and this Examinant ſaith, that about two moneths ſince, being in her bed, in the night, ſomething fell down upon her right ſide, but being dark, ſhe cannot tell in what ſhape it was: And that preſently ſhee was taken lame on that ſide, with extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary pains and burning, but recovered again within a few dayes after: And this Informant further ſaith, that ſhe verily believeth, that <hi>Rebecca Weſt,</hi> and <hi>Anne Weſt</hi> her mother, were the cauſe of her pains; for that the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi> hath in part of her Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion expreſſed, that ſhee had much maliced this Informant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſaid <hi>Rebecca Weſt</hi> ever thought this Informant to be her greateſt enemy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>John Edes,</hi> Clerke, taken upon <hi>oath before the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>day of Aprill.</hi> 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, That <hi>Rebecca Weſte</hi> confeſſed unto him, that about ſeven yeares ſince, ſhee began to have familiaritie with the Devill, by the inſtigation of her mother <hi>Anne Weſte;</hi> who hath appeared unto the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi> at ſeverall times, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe ſhapes: At one time in the likeneſſe of a proper young man, who deſired of her, that he might have the ſame familiaritie with her, that others that appeared unto her before had had: Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that if ſhee would, he would then doe for the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi> what ſhe deſired, and avenge her on her enemies; but required further; that ſhee would deny God, and relie upon him. Now there was one <hi>Thomas Hart</hi> of <hi>Lawford,</hi> where the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:130529:11"/>lived with her ſaid mother, <hi>Anne Weſt,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi> told this Informant, that ſhee required of him, that hee would avenge her on the ſaid. <hi>Hart</hi> by killing his ſon, who not long after was taken ſick, and dyed, whereupon the ſaid. <hi>Rebecca</hi> told this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, that ſhee conceived hee could do as God; after which time ſhee gave entertainment to him, who lay with her as a man; and the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi> further confeſſed to this Informant, that whileſt ſhe lived at <hi>Rivenall</hi> in the ſaid. County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Anne</hi> her mother, came to the ſaid <hi>Rebecca,</hi> and told her the Barley corn was picked up (meaning one <hi>George Frances</hi> (the only ſon of one <hi>George Frances,</hi> one of the chief Inhabitants of that town, where the ſaid <hi>Anne Weſt</hi> dwelt) and that his father thought the ſaid <hi>George</hi> his ſon was bewitched to death; and the ſaid <hi>Anne</hi> then ſaid unto the ſaid <hi>Rebecca, Be it unto him according to his faith.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Confeſſion of <hi>Rebecca Weſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Found by the grand Jury, but acquitted by the Jury of life and death.</note> taken before the ſaid <hi>Juſtices at</hi> Mannyntree, <hi>the</hi> 21. <hi>of</hi> March, 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant ſaith, that about a moneth ſince, the aforeſaid <hi>Anne Leech, Elizabeth Gooding, Hellen Clark, Anne Weſt,</hi> and this Examinant, met all together at the houſe of the aforeſaid <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth Clark</hi> in <hi>Mannyntree,</hi> where they together ſpent ſome time in praying unto their Familiars, and every one in order went to prayers; afterwards ſome of them read in a book, the book being <hi>Elizabeth Clarks;</hi> and this Examinant ſaith, that forthwith their Familiars appeared, and every one of them made their ſeverall Propoſitions to thoſe Familiars, what every one of them deſired to have effected: And this Examinant ſaith, that firſt of all the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Clark</hi> deſired of her Spirit, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Edwards</hi> might be met withall about the middle bridge, as hee ſhould come riding from <hi>Eaſtberyhoult</hi> in <hi>Suffolk;</hi> that his Horſe might be ſcared, and he thrown down, and never riſe again: And this Examinant ſaith, that the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Gooding</hi> deſired of her Spirit, that ſhee might be avenged on <hi>Robert Taylers</hi> Horſe, for that the ſaid <hi>Robert</hi> ſuſpected the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Gooding</hi> for the killing of an Horſe of the ſaid <hi>Robert</hi> formerly: And this examinant ſaith, that the ſaid <hi>Hellen Clark</hi> deſired of her Spirit, that ſhee might be reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:130529:11"/>on two Hogs in <hi>Miſley ſtreet,</hi> (being the place where the ſaid <hi>Hellen</hi> lived) one of the Hogs to die preſently, and the other to be taken lame; and this Examinant further ſaith, that <hi>Anne Leeeb</hi> deſired of her Spirit, that a Cowe might be taken lame of a mans living in <hi>Mannyntree,</hi> but the name of the man this Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant cannot remember: And this examinant further ſaith, that the ſaid <hi>Anne Weſt,</hi> this Examinants mother,
<note place="margin">This <hi>Anne Weſt</hi> was exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted at <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyntree</hi> the firſt of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt.</hi> 1645.</note> deſired of her Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that ſhee might be freed from all her enemies, and have no trouble: And this Examinant ſaith, that ſhee deſired of her Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that ſhee might be revenged on <hi>Prudence</hi> the wife of <hi>Thomas Hart,</hi> and that the ſaid <hi>Prudence</hi> might be taken lame on her right ſide. And laſtly this Examinant ſaith, that having thus done, this Examinant, and the other five, did appoint the next meeting to be at the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Goodings</hi> houſe, and ſo depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all to their owne houſes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Richard Edwards</hi> of <hi>Mannintree, Gent. taken upon oath before the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 23<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>of Aprill.</hi> 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, That not long ſince, about three moneths to his beſt remembrance, as he was coming from <hi>Eaſtberyholt</hi> in <hi>Suffolke,</hi> halfe an houre within evening; within ten ſcore of the middle bridge (according to the deſire of the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Clarke,</hi> as is declared in the confeſſion of the ſaid <hi>Rebecca Weſte</hi>) this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formants horſe ſtarted with him, and greatly endangered him; and he heard ſomething about his horſe cry, Ah, ah; much like the ſhrieke of a Polcat. And this Informant ſaith, That with much difficulty he ſaved himſelfe from being thrown off his horſe. All which, this Informant reported to his wife and neighbours as ſoone as he came home.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Matthew Hopkins,</hi> Gent. taken <hi>upon oath before the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>of Aprill.</hi> 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, That being lately at <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> he went to the Caſtle, where the ſaid <hi>Rebecca Weſte,</hi> with the other five,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:130529:12"/>are ſecured untill the next Gaole delivery: And this Informant going to <hi>Rebeeca Weſte,</hi> and asking her how ſhee came firſt to be a Witch, the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi> told this Informant, that about a yeare fince, or thereabouts, halfe an houre before Sun-ſet, the ſaid <hi>Anne Weſte</hi> (her mother) carried the ſaid <hi>Rebecca Weſte</hi> towards <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nintree,</hi> (which is about a ſmall mile from the place where the ſaid <hi>Anne</hi> dwelt) and the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi> told this Informant, that as her mother and ſhee walked together, the ſaid <hi>Anne</hi> told the ſaid <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca,</hi> ſhee muſt keepe ſecret whatſoever ſhee ſaw, whither they were then going; and the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi> promiſed ſo to doe; And the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi> told this Informant, that her mother and ſhee went to the houſe of the aforeſaid <hi>Elizabeth Clarke,</hi> where at their comming in they found the aforeſaid <hi>Anne Leech,</hi> widow, <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Gooding, Hellen Clarke,</hi> and the houſe-keeper <hi>Elizabeth Clarke,</hi> and that forthwith the Devill appeared to them in the ſhape of a dogge; afterwards in the ſhape of two Kitlyns; then in the ſhape of two dogges; and that the ſaid familiars did doe homage in the firſt place to the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Clarke,</hi> and skipped up into her lap, and kiſſed her; and then went and kiſſed all that were in the roome, except the ſaid <hi>Rebecca:</hi> And the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi> told this Informant, that immediately one of their company asked the ſaid <hi>Anne</hi> her mother, if ſhee had acquainted her daughter (the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi>) with the buſineſſe; and her mother anſwered ſhee had, and told them all, they need not feare her the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi> for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing any thing: And the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi> told this Informant, that forthwith the ſaid <hi>Anne Leech</hi> pulled out a booke, and ſwore the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi> never to reveale any thing ſhee ſaw or heard; and if ſhee ſhould diſcover any thing, they all told the ſaid <hi>Rebecca,</hi> ſhee ſhould endure more torments on earth, then could be in hell: And the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi> told this Informant, that ſhee promiſed to keepe all their ſecrets; And moreover, they all told her, that ſhee muſt never confeſſe any thing, although the Rope were about her necke, and ſhee ready to be hanged: And that after ſhee had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to all theſe things, the Devill came into her lap, and kiſſed her, and promiſed to doe for her what ſhee could deſire; and that within halfe a yeare after the Devill appeared to her the ſaid <hi>Rebecca,</hi> as ſhee was going to bed, and told her, he would marry her, and that ſhee could not deny him; ſhee ſaid he kiſſed her,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:130529:12"/>but was as cold as clay, and married her that night, in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; He tooke her by the hand and lead her about the Chamber, and promiſed to be her loving husband till death, and to avenge her of her enemies; And that then ſhee promiſed him to be his obedient wife till death, and to deny God and Chriſt Jeſus; And the ſaid <hi>Rebecca</hi> told this Informant, that ſhee ſent the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill to kill the ſonne of the ſaid <hi>Thomas Hart,</hi> which he did within one fortnight; and that after that ſhee tooke him for her God, and thought he could doe as God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Suſan Sparrow,</hi> taken upon oath <hi>before the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>day of Aprill. An. Dom.</hi> 1645. <hi>at</hi> Little Bentley.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, That about thirty yeares ſince, living un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame roofe with <hi>Mary Greenleif</hi> of <hi>Alresford,</hi> either of them had a Daughter of about thirteen or fourteen yeares of age, and being one night in bed with their children, this Informant heard the childe of the ſaid <hi>Mary Greenleif</hi> to cry out in a fearefull manner; Oh Mother, now it comes, it comes, oh helpe mother, it hurts me, it hurts me: Whereupon this Informant called to the ſaid <hi>Mary,</hi> and ſaid, Good-wife <hi>Greenleife,</hi> Good-wife <hi>Greenleife,</hi> if your childe be aſleepe, awaken it, for if any body comes by, and heare it make ſuch moane (you having an ill name already) they will ſay, You are ſuckling your Impes upon it: Whereupon the ſaid <hi>Mary</hi> replyed; I doe ſo indeed, and I will fee with them (meaning her ſaid Impes,) that they ſhall ſuck my daughter one night, and thine another: And this Informant ſaith, that the very next night, her childe cryed out in the ſame manner, and claſped her armes about this Informants necke, being much affrighted, ſweating, and ſhrieking in a terrible manner, complaining that ſhee was nipped and pinched on her thigh; and that the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſearching what the cauſe ſhould be, ſhee found above the right knee of her childe, a black and blew ſpot, as broad and long as her hand: And this Informant ſaith, that her childe did complaine on that leg, at leaſt a moneth after. And this Informant ſaith, that the houſe where this Informant and the ſaid <hi>Mary</hi> did dwell
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:130529:13"/>together, was haunted with a Leveret, which did uſually fit before the dore: And this Informant knowing that one <hi>Anthony Shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi> had an excellent Greyhound that had killed many Hares; and having heard that a childe of the ſaid <hi>Anthony</hi> was much haunted and troubled, and that the mother of the childe ſuſpected the ſaid <hi>Mary</hi> to be the cauſe of it: This Informant went to the ſaid <hi>Anthony Sharlock</hi> and acquainted him, that a Leveret did uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally come and ſit before the dore, where this Informant and the ſaid <hi>Mary Greenleife</hi> lived, and deſired the ſaid <hi>Anthony</hi> to bring downe his Greyhond to ſee if he could kill the ſaid Leveret; and the next day the ſaid <hi>Anthony</hi> did accordingly bring his Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound, and courſed it, but whether the dog killed it this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant knows not; But being a little before courſed by Good-man <hi>Merrills</hi> dog, the dog ran at it, but the Leveret never ſtirred, and juſt when the dog came at it, he skipped over it, and turned about and ſtood ſtill, and looked on it, and ſhortly after that dog lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed and dyed. But whether this was an Impe in the ſhape of a Leveret, or had any relation to the ſaid <hi>Mary,</hi> this Informant knows not, but does confeſſe ſhee wondered very much to ſee a Leveret, wilde by nature, to come ſo frequently and ſit openly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the dore in ſuch a familiar way.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Elizabeth Hunt</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla Brigs, taken upon oath before the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>day of Aprill.</hi> 1645.</head>
            <p>THeſe Informants ſay, That being by the ſaid Juſtices imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſearch the ſaid <hi>Mary Greenleife,</hi> upon ſuſpect for being a Witch, theſe Informants found that the ſaid <hi>Mary</hi> had bigges or teates in her ſecret parts, not like Emerods, nor in thoſe places where women uſe to be troubled with them; and that they verily beleeve, theſe teates are ſucked by her Impes; for that theſe Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mants have been formerly imployed to ſearch other women ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted for Witchcraft, who have had the like bigges, and have after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards confeſſed themſelves to be Witches.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:130529:13"/>
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Mary Greenleife</hi> taken before the <hi>ſaid Juſtices,</hi> April 25. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant being asked how ſhe came by thoſe teats which were diſcovered in her ſecret parts, She ſaith ſhe knows not unleſſe ſhe were born with them; but ſhe neven knew ſhe had any ſuch untill this time, they were found in thoſe parts upon the ſaid ſearch; And ſhe does deny that ever ſhe had any Impe ſucked on theſe teats: But ſhe does confeſſe ſhe hath ſeen a <hi>Leveret</hi> once ſitting before her doore within a yard of the threſhold; and that ſhe wondered much at it, being about noon time as ſhe remembreth. And further ſaith, ſhe is not guilty of any accuſation charged upon her this Examinant.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Elizabeth Otley</hi> of <hi>Wyvenhoe</hi> taken <hi>upon oath before the ſaid Juſtices,</hi> April 25. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, that <hi>Alice Dixon</hi> (who now ſtands committed for a ſuſpected Witch) did in the preſence of <hi>Mary Johnſon</hi> of the ſame Town, charge and accuſe the ſaid <hi>Mary Johnſon</hi> to be the death of his Informants child, ſaying, that the ſaid <hi>Mary Johnſon</hi> did carry an Impe in her pocket to this Informants houſe, and put the ſaid Impe into the houſe, at an hole in the doore, bidding it go rock the Cradle, and do the buſineſſe ſhe ſent it about, and return to her again: And this Informant ſaith, that upon a Munday before Michaelmas laſt, the ſaid <hi>Mary Johnſon</hi> came to the houſe of this Informant, and gave her child an apple, and kiſſed it; And within a ſhort time after the ſaid child ſickned and died: And the ſaid <hi>Alice Dixon</hi> did alſo affirm, that the Impe which the ſaid <hi>Mary Johnſon</hi> ſent to this Informants houſe, was in ſhape ſomewhat like a Rat, but without tayl and eares. And this Informant ſaith, that the ſaid <hi>Mary Johnſons</hi> anſwer was, that if ſhe did it, ſhe did it, ſhe could but receive puniſhment for it. And at the ſame time the ſaid <hi>Mary Johnſon</hi> ſaid, the ſaid <hi>Alice Dixon</hi> did the miſchief to this Informants child her ſelf. And this Informant further
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:130529:14"/>ſaith, that after the ſaid <hi>Alice Dixon</hi> had made this diſcovery, ſhe, this Informant, was taken with extreme pains in her body, and that during the time of her extremity, the ſaid <hi>Mary John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> did many times come to this Informants houſe, perſwading her, that ſhe was not the death of this Informants child: But this Informant could not be ſatisfied untill ſhe had gotten the blood of the ſaid <hi>Mary Johnſon;</hi> And meeting with her after long ſcuffling, this Informant made the ſaid <hi>Mary Johnſons</hi> teeth to bleed, and immediately after, this Informants extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary pains left her, and her ſtomack came to her, having eat little or nothing a fortnight before, and ſlept very well the night following, having been reſtleſſe by reaſon of her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme pains all the time aforeſaid. And this Informant fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, that the next day after the ſaid <hi>Mary Johnſon</hi> had given this Informants child the Apple, the child was taken with very violent fits, and in the fits (although the Child was but two yeers old) yet this Informant could very hardly with all her ſtrength hold it down in the Cradle, and ſo continued untill it died.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Mary Johnſon</hi> taken before the ſaid <hi>Juſtices the</hi> 25. <hi>of</hi> April, 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant ſaith, that ſhe is not guilty of any one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular charged upon her in the Information of the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Otley</hi> touching the killing of the child of the ſaid <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Ioſeph Long</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Clacton</hi> in <hi>the County of</hi> Eſſex, <hi>taken before the ſaid Juſt:</hi> April 29. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith,
<note place="margin">Executed at <hi>Mannintree</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Auguſt.</note> that <hi>Anne</hi> the wife of <hi>John Cooper</hi> of <hi>Clacton</hi> aforeſaid, being accuſed for a Witch: Confeſſed unto this Informant, that ſhe the ſaid <hi>Anne</hi> was guilty of the ſin of Witchcraft; and that ſhe hath had three black Impes ſuckled on the lower parts of her body: called by the names of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:130529:14"/>
               <hi>Wynowe, Jeſo,</hi> and <hi>Panu:</hi> And this Informant ſaith, that the ſaid <hi>Anne</hi> told him, that once ſhe curſed a Colt of one <hi>William Cottingams</hi> of Clacton aforeſaid, and the ſaid Colt broke his neck preſently after going out of a gate: And the ſaid <hi>Anne</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confeſſed unto this Informant, that ſhe the ſaid <hi>Anne</hi> offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to give unto her daughter <hi>Sarah Cooper</hi> an Impe in the likenes of a gray Kite, to ſuck on the ſaid <hi>Sarah:</hi> which Impes name the ſaid <hi>Anne</hi> called <hi>Tom boy:</hi> and told the ſaid <hi>Sarah,</hi> there was a Cat for her; And this Informant ſaith, that the ſaid <hi>Anne</hi> confeſſed unto him, that ſhe the ſaid <hi>Anne</hi> about ten yeers fince falling out with <hi>Johan</hi> the wife of <hi>Gregory Rous</hi> of Clacton a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; the ſaid <hi>Anne Cooper</hi> ſent one of her Impes to kill the daughter of the ſaid <hi>Gregory</hi> and <hi>Johan</hi> named <hi>Mary:</hi> And this Informant ſaith, that to his own knowledge about the ſame time the ſaid child was ſtrangely taken fick, and languiſhing, within a ſhort time died.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Roger Hempſon</hi> taken upon oath <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid Juſtices,</hi> April 29. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant doth confirm the Information of the ſaid <hi>Joſeph Longe,</hi> and concurs in every particular.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Roger Hempſon</hi> taken upon oath <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid Juſtices,</hi> April 29. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, that Mr. <hi>Longe</hi> telling <hi>Elizabeth Hare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Condemned, but reprieved.</note> that ſhe was accuſed by one <hi>Mary Smith,</hi> for giving of her the ſaid <hi>Mary</hi> two Impes: And that the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Hare,</hi> praying to God with her hands upward, that if ſhe were guilty of any ſuch thing, He would ſhew ſome example upon her: And this Informant ſaith, that preſently after ſhe ſhaked and quivered, and fell down to the ground backward, and tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled up and down upon the ground, and hath continued ſick ever fince.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:130529:15"/>
            <head>The Information of <hi>Anaball</hi> the wife of <hi>George Durrant taken upon oath before the ſaid Juſtices,</hi> April 29. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, that about ten moneths fince, going from <hi>Wivenhoe</hi> towards <hi>Fingeringhoe,</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> by the way <hi>Mary Johnſon</hi> the wife of <hi>Nicholas Johnſon</hi> met with this Informant, whom this Informant never ſaw before to her knowledge; And this Informant leading her Child up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her hand, being about two yeers old, and perfectly well: the ſaid <hi>Mary Johnſon</hi> took occaſion of her own accord to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the ſaid Child, ſaying, it was a pretty child; and ſtroa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked it upon the face, and gave it a peece of bread and butter, and ſo left this Informant. And this Informants child did eat a peece of the ſaid bread and butter: and within half a quarter of an houre after, her ſaid child ſhricked and dried out it was lame; And this Informant carried her child home, and had the advice of one Mr. <hi>Dawber</hi> a Chirurgeon, who could find no na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall cauſe of its lameneſſe; and ſo the ſaid child continued for the ſpace of eight dayes ſhricking and tearing it ſelf, and then died.</p>
            <p>And further, this Informant ſaith, that immediately after the death of her child, ſhe was taken with extremepains in her body, ſometimes every day or at leaſt every third day, for the ſpace of ſeven or eight moneths together as if ſhe had been to be delivered of a child, but was not with child; And this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant ſaith, that ſetting up of broome in an out-houſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after her child was dead, ſhe had the perfect repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a ſhape, to her thinking, like the ſaid <hi>Mary Johnſon,</hi> and was ſtruck with a lameneſſe in her Arms, and ſuch a ſtiffneſſe that three or foure that came to help her, were not able to bow her Arms: and this Informant continued ſpeechloſſe all that day and the night following, and had ſuch a weakneſſe in the reſt of her limbes, that ſhe was carried into her houſe by ſome of her friends, and continued by the ſpace of a fortnight, being before untill this preſent (as ſhe conceived) in perfect health and ſtrength: And further this Informant ſaith, that ſhe being
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:130529:15"/>charged by the Conſtable by vertue of a Warrant to give this her Information before the ſaid Juſtices againſt the ſaid <hi>Mary Johnſon</hi> this day: this Informants husband called her up in the morning, wiſhing her to make her ready to go before the ſaid Juſtices; And preſently after he gave a great ſhrick, and ſaid the ſaid <hi>Mary Johnſon</hi> would be his death, and had a great ſwelling riſen up in his breaſt, and now lies ſweating, and in great extremity. And at this very inſtant a noiſe was heard in the Roome where her husband lay like an Hornet, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon her husband cried out, It comes, it comes, Now good wife <hi>Johnſons</hi> Impe is come, Now ſhe hath my life; And forthwith a great part of the wall in the ſaid roome fell down. And this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant ſaith, that ſhe doth verily beleeve the ſaid <hi>Mary John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> was the cauſe of her childs death: And that ſhe is now the cauſe of her husbands extremity.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Ric. Carter</hi> and <hi>Heary-Cornwall</hi> of Thorp, <hi>taken upon oath before the ſaid Juſtices,</hi> April 29. 1645.</head>
            <p>THeſe Informants ſay, that being appointed to watch <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet Moone,</hi> after ſhe was accuſed and apprehended for a Witch, the ſaid <hi>Margaret</hi> going about the Roome, theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formants did ſee a thing drop from under her coats (as they thought) in the likeneſſe of a Rat for bigneſſe and ſhape, but of a greyer colour; And preſently there was ſuch an extreame offen five ſtink in the Roome, that theſe Informants were ſcarce able to endure to ſtay in it; And theſe Informants asking the ſaid <hi>Margaret</hi> what it was that dropped from her, ſhe bids them coop it up and catch it if they could. And this Informant <hi>Henry Cornwall</hi> ſaith, that the ſaid <hi>Margaret</hi> did confeſſe to him that ſhe had twelve Impes, and called them by their names; of which he remembers onely theſe following: <hi>Jeſus, Jockey, Sandy, Mris. Elizabeth,</hi> and <hi>Collyn.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:130529:16"/>
            <head>The Information of <hi>Will. Dammon, Hen. Cornwall, Bevis</hi> Vincent, <hi>and</hi> Tho. Burles, <hi>taken upon oath before the ſaid Juſtices,</hi> April 29. 1645.</head>
            <p>THeſe Informants ſay, that upon the 21. day of <hi>April</hi> laſt paſt, they heard <hi>Margaret Moone</hi> confeſſe, that ſhe was a Witch, and that ſhe had twelve Impes, that ſhe had killed a Cow of <hi>Stephen Cookers,</hi> and had two Cowes more of the ſaid <hi>Stephen</hi> in handling; that ſhe had killed a Cow and a Sow of <hi>Henry Robertſons.</hi> That ſhe was partner with the aforeſaid <hi>Eliz: Clark</hi> of Mannintree, in killing of a Child of one Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> of Mannintree aforeſaid, and ſpoiling of 3 Brewings of beere of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Edwards.</hi> That ſhe the ſaid <hi>Margaret Moon</hi> ſpoiled a batch of bread of one <hi>Philip Berrimans;</hi> that ſhe was the cauſe that one <hi>Philip Daniels</hi> horſe broke his neck going down an hill in his Waggon. And the ſaid Informant ſaith, that the ſaid <hi>M: Moone</hi> did freely and voluntarily confeſſe unto him, without any queſtion being asked, that ſhe was the cauſe of the death of <hi>Johan Cornwall</hi> this Informants daughter. And this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant ſaith, that the ſaid <hi>Margaret Moone</hi> before his child fell ſick, ſent for this Informant to do ſome work for her, and then ſhe deſired to buy an Hooke which he carried with him in his hand; And they agreed ſhe ſhould have the ſaid Hooke for half a peck of Apples: And as this Informant went home he did eat one of the ſaid Apples, and was preſently taken ſick with an extreme ſhaking and pain in all parts of his body; And his Informants wife knowing the ſaid <hi>Margaret Moone</hi> to be a woman of a very bad fame and ſuſpected for a Witch, and had formerly been queſtioned at an Aſſize for the ſame, ſhe flung away the Aples. And this Informant ſaith, that he continued in great extremity for the ſpace of twelve weeks, and moſt part of tha; time deprived of his ſenſes. And at the ſame time his wife was taken in the ſame manner, and is not yet perfectly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered. And laſtly this Informant ſaith, that the next day after he had been at the ſaid <hi>Margarets</hi> houſe as aforeſaid, that his child (which the ſaid <hi>Margaret</hi> confeſſed ſhe was the death of) was taken ſick with ſtrange fits, and ſhrickings out, and ſo continued languiſhing for a moneth, and died.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:130529:16"/>
            <head>The Information of <hi>Richard Caley</hi> of <hi>Thorpe</hi> taken upon <hi>oath before the ſaid Juſtices,</hi> April 29. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, that being called into the houſe where <hi>Bevis Vincent,</hi> and <hi>Henry Cornwall</hi> were appointed by the neighbours of <hi>Thorpe</hi> aforeſaid to watch <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret Moone,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Margaret</hi> did confeſſe before this Informant, that ſhe had by Witchcraft killed a Cow and a Sow of one <hi>Henry Robinſons.</hi> And that one <hi>Henry Dorr</hi> being then called to write what ſhe ſhould confeſſe, the ſaid <hi>Margaret</hi> refuſed to make any further diſcovery, before this Informant; but fell upon other diſcourſe, ſaying, that ſhe had been told fourty times, that this Informant thought in his conſcience ſhe was no Witch: And that this Informant knew that one <hi>William Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> his brother let the ſaid <hi>Margaret</hi> an Houſe about twenty yeers ſince, and afterwards warned her out of the ſaid houſe; and that then ſhe went into an houſe that was built for her by one <hi>Thomas Turner,</hi> and being alſo turned out of <hi>Turners</hi> houſe, that one <hi>Rawbood</hi> and his wife gave ten ſhillings more for the ſaid houſe, then the ſaid <hi>Margaret,</hi> and came and dwelt in the ſaid houſe: But the ſaid <hi>Margaret</hi> ſaid, they (meaning the ſaid <hi>Rawbood</hi> and his wife) had as good they had not medled with the houſe, for they did never thrive after. And this Informant ſaith, that after the ſaid <hi>Rawbood</hi> had taken the ſaid houſe, he and his wife were alwayes lame or ſick untill they died: and that the wife of the ſaid <hi>Rawbood</hi> being a very tydy and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly woman, ſitting upon a block after dinner with another Neighbour a little before it was time to go to Church (and as he remembers) upon an Eaſter day, the ſaid <hi>Rawboods</hi> wife was on the ſudden ſo filled with Lice, that they might have been ſwept off her cloaths with a ſtick; And this Informant ſaith he did ſee them, and that they were long, and lean, and not like other Lice. And this Informant being asked, whether the ſaid <hi>Margaret</hi> were at this time ſenſible, he ſaith that ſhe ſpake very plainly and very intelligently, diſcourſing of ſome things done long before, her memory ſerving her very exactly.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:130529:17"/>
            <head>The Information of <hi>Francis Milles</hi> taken upon oath <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid Juſtices,</hi> April 29. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, that being imployed by the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of <hi>Thorpe</hi> aforeſaid, to ſearch <hi>Margaret Moone,</hi> who was ſuſpected for a Witch, ſhe found three long teats or bigges in her ſecret parts, which ſeemed to have been lately ſucked; and that they were not like Pyles, for this Informant knows well what they are, having been troubled with them her ſelf. And this Informant ſaith, that ſhe asking the ſaid <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi> for her Impes, which ſucked thoſe teats: ſhe ſaid, if ſhe might have ſome bread and beere, ſhe would call her ſaid Impes; which being given unto her, ſhe put the bread into the beere, and ſet it againſt an hole in the wall, and made a circle round about the pot, and then cried, Come Chriſt, come Chriſt, come Mounſier, come Mounſier: And no Impe appearing, ſhe cried out and ſaid, ſhe had Devilliſh Daughters which had car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried her Impes away in a white bagge, and wiſhed they might be ſearched, for they were naught: And upon the ſearching of her Daughters, this Informant found that two of them had biggs in their privy parts as the ſaid <hi>Margaret</hi> their mother had.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Mary Philips, Elizabeth Harris, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,</hi> Suſan Burles, <hi>and</hi> Philip Tumnor <hi>taken upon oath before the ſaid Juſtices,</hi> April 29. 1645.</head>
            <p>THeſe Informants do all and every of them concur with <hi>Frances Milles</hi> in her ſaid Information, in that particular concerning the teats of the ſaid <hi>Margaret Moone,</hi> and her two daughters; And the ſaid <hi>Mary Philips</hi> doth alſo confirm and concur with that part of the Information of the ſaid <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Milles,</hi> touching the pot, the circle, and the calling of the Impes by the ſaid <hi>Margaret Moone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this Informant <hi>Mary Philips</hi> doth alſo ſay, that being ſent for to ſearch the ſaid <hi>Margaret Moone,</hi> as ſhe was coming
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:130529:17"/>towards <hi>Thorp</hi> aforeſaid, and going over a broad foot Bridge, this Informant ſenſibly felt a great blow on her head, which ſtrook her into a ditch up to the neck. And this Informant and the ſaid <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Mylles,</hi> doe both of them ſay, That as ſoon as they came into the room where the ſaid <hi>Margaret Moon</hi> was, ſhe called theſe two Informants, <hi>Mannintree Rogues</hi> (they both dwelling at a Town ſo called,) and ſaid, Who a Devill ſent for you? But I hope I have met with ſome of you.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Margaret Moon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Condemned and dyed by the way to execution.</note> taken before <hi>the ſaid Juſtices, the</hi> 29. <hi>day of May,</hi> 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant being examined to all the particulars charged upon her, in all the aforeſaid ſeverall informations, denies eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Judith Moone,</hi> daughter of the <hi>ſaid</hi> Margaret Moone, <hi>taken before the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>day of Aprill.</hi> 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant (being a ſingle woman and having ſuch marks of a Witch, as aforeſaid) ſaith, that about a fortnight before her Mother was apprehended for a Witch, the ſaid <hi>Margaret</hi> bid this Examinant goe and fetch a bundle of wood, and this Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant told her mother ſhee would not fetch any wood: Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſaid <hi>Margaret</hi> threatned this Examinant, and told her ſhee had as good have gone for ſome wood; And that the next night as this Examinant lay in her bed, ſhe felt ſomething come into the bed, about her legges, being at that time broad awake, and that ſhee ſearched to ſee what it ſhould be, but could not finde any thing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:130529:18"/>
            <head>The Information of <hi>Bridget Reynolds,</hi> the wife of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Reynolds of</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amſey <hi>in the ſaid County of</hi> Eſſex, <hi>taken upon oath before the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of</hi> May. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, That ſhe with ſome other women, were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sarah Hiting,</hi> the wife of <hi>William H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing, Elizabeth Harvy,</hi> widow, and <hi>marian Hocket,</hi> widow, who are all ſuſpected for witchcraft, and upon her ſaid ſearch (being a Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife) found ſuch Marks, or Bigges in their privy parts, that ſhe never ſaw in other women: for <hi>Sarah Hating</hi> had foure Teats, or Bigges in thoſe parts, almoſt an inch long, and as bigge as this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formants little finger: That the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Harvy</hi> had three ſuch Bigges, and about the ſaid ſcantling: And that the ſaid <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Hocke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> had no ſuch bigges; but was found in the ſame parts not like other honeſt women. And this Informant further ſaith. That the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Harvy</hi> ſaid (ſince ſhe was found with the ſaid ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious marks) unto this Informant, That if ſhe were a Witch, ſhe was ſo made by the ſaid <hi>Marian Hocket;</hi> for that the ſaid <hi>Marian</hi> brought unto her the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Harrvy,</hi> three things about the bigneſſe of Mouſes, and willed the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to make much of them, for they were pretty things; which the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: And the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> told this Informant, that ever ſince ſhe received thoſe three things which the ſaid <hi>Marian</hi> delivered unto her, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he hath been much torn and troubled in her privy parts, where the ſaid Bigges were found. And that the ſaid three things were delivered to her the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> about ſix or ſeven years ſince.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Elizabeth Durden,</hi> the wife of <hi>Edw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mary Philips,</hi> taken upon oath before <hi>the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>day of</hi> May 1645.</head>
            <p>THeſe Informants do concurre in every particular with the ſaid <hi>Briget Reynolds</hi> in her Information touching the ſearch of the ſaid <hi>Sarah Haring, Elizabeth Harvie,</hi> and <hi>Marian Hocket:</hi> And this Informant <hi>Elizabeth Durden</hi> further ſaith, that the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Harvie</hi> told her, that if ſhee were a Witch, ſhee was ſo made by the ſaid <hi>Marian Hocket.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:130529:18"/>
            <head>The Information of <hi>Francis Stock</hi> and <hi>John Batilly, taken upon oath, before the ſaid Juſtices,</hi> May 3. 1645.</head>
            <p>THeſe Informants ſay, that the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Harvie</hi> confeſſed to them with many teares, that ſhee had three marks, two be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and one behinder (as is already informed by <hi>Bridget Reynolds</hi> and others,) And that the ſaid <hi>Marian Hocket</hi> made her have the ſaid marks or bigs, by bringing of three things to her the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and telling her, if ſhee would receive them, ſhee ſhould never in no ſo long as ſhe liveth, which three things have ſince made the ſaid marks in her privie parts, and the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> told theſe Informants, that the ſaid three things were of a reddiſh color, and that ſince, the ſaid <hi>Marian,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> falling out, ſhe the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> would have put away &amp; ſent home the three things which the ſaid <hi>Marian</hi> brought to her, and that ever ſince the ſaid things have tormented her in her bed, in the places afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, as if they had pulled her in pieces.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The ſecond Information of <hi>Francis Stock,</hi> taken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid Juſtices upon oath, <hi>May</hi> 3. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, that about five yeers ſince, being one of the Conſtables of <hi>Ramſey</hi> aforeſaid, hee impreſſed <hi>William Hiting,</hi> husband to the aforeſaid <hi>Sarah Hating</hi> for a ſouldier, whereupon the ſaid <hi>William</hi> threatened this Informant very much, and not long after, this Informants wife told him, ſhee eſpied a Snake lying upon a ſhelf in this Informants houſe, about three yards high from the ground, which falling down into the houſe, ſhee endeavoured to kill with a ſpade; and ſtriking at it, the Snake ſuddenly vaniſhed away, and could no where be found: And this Informant ſaith, that preſently after his ſaid wife was taken ſick with extraordinary fits, pains and burnings all over her body, and within one week dyed: And further this Informant ſaith, that within two or three dayes, after the death of his ſaid wife, hee had a daughter taken ſick after a very ſtrange manner, who in all the time of her ſickneſſe, cryed out much on the ſaid
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:130529:19"/>
               <hi>Sarah,</hi> the wife of the ſaid <hi>William Hating,</hi> ſaying, that the ſaid <hi>Sarah</hi> was the cauſe of her death, and dyed preſently after; and that within two or three dayes after the death of his ſaid childe, this Informant had another childe taken ſick in the ſame manner, and within a few dayes dyed alſo: And laſtly, this Informant ſaith, that about three quarters of a yeer after, he had a man-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, that for ſome ill language given to him by <hi>John Hating,</hi> one of the ſons of the ſaid <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Sarah Hating,</hi> his ſaid ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant did beat the ſaid <hi>John,</hi> and the very next day hee was taken ſick, and ſo continued in a pining and languiſhing condition, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out often of the ſaid <hi>Sarah,</hi> that ſhe had bewitched him, and was the cauſe of his death, which ſoon after enſued.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Francis Stock,</hi> and <hi>John Felgate, taken upon oath before the ſaid Juſtices,</hi> May 3. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Informant <hi>John Felgate</hi> ſaith, that ſpeaking with one <hi>Sarah Barton,</hi> the ſiſter of the ſaid <hi>Marian Hocket</hi> (which ſaid <hi>Sarah</hi> is now impriſoned in the Gaole at <hi>Harwich</hi> upon ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Witchcraft) who told this Informant, that the ſaid <hi>Marian</hi> had cut off her bigs, whereby ſhe might have been the more ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to have been a Witch, and laid plaiſters to thoſe places: And the ſaid <hi>Francis</hi> and <hi>John</hi> ſay, that the ſaid <hi>Sarah Barton,</hi> told them, that the ſaid <hi>Marian</hi> had given and delivered unto her the ſaid <hi>Sarah</hi> three Imps, and that the ſaid <hi>Marian</hi> called them by the names of <hi>Littleman, Pretty-man,</hi> and <hi>Dainty.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Marian Hocket, Sarah Hating,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth Harvie</hi> of <hi>Ramſey</hi> within the County aforeſaid, <hi>taken before the ſaid Juſtices,</hi> May 3. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant,
<note place="margin">Executed at <hi>Mannyutree,</hi> Aug. 1. 1645.</note> 
               <hi>Marian Hocket</hi> ſaith, that ſhee is not guilty of any of the particulars charged upon her, touching Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, notwitſtanding the ſeverall accuſations againſt her.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:130529:19"/>
THis Examinant, <hi>Sarah Hating</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Executed at <hi>Chelmesford.</hi>
               </note> that ſhee is not guilty of any particular wherewith ſhee ſtands charged in the Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Francis Stock</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>THis Examinant, <hi>Elizabeth Harvie</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Executed at <hi>Chelmesford.</hi>
               </note> that about halfe a yeer ſince, the ſaid <hi>Marian Hocket</hi> brought three things to her houſe, two of them being ſmaller then Mouſes, and the other ſomewhat bigger and longer; and that the ſaid <hi>Marian</hi> told this examinant they were pretty things, and would do her and this Examinant good, if ſhee this Examinant would keep them; and that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſhee was very much pained in thoſe parts of her body where the ſaid tears or bigs were diſcovered by the ſaid ſearchers, as aforeſaid.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Robert Turner</hi> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Oſith</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter, taken upon oath before the ſaid Juſtices, <hi>May</hi> 6. 1465.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, that about eight dayes ſince, his ſervant was taken ſick, ſhaking and ſhricking, and crying out of <hi>Roſe Hallybread,</hi> that ſhee had bewitched him: And this Informant ſaith, that ſometimes his ſaid ſervant, ſince hee was taken ſick, as aforeſaid, hath crowed perfectly as a Cock; ſometimes barked like a Dog; ſometimes violently groaned beyond the ordinary courſe of nature; and ſtrugling with ſuch ſtrength (being but a youth) that four or five ſtrong men were not able to hold him down in his bed; and ſometimes ſung divers and ſundry perfect tunes: And that this Informant could not perceive his mouth to open, or ſo much as his lips to ſtir all the time of his ſinging.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Roſe Hallybread,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Died in the Gaole.</note> taken before <hi>the ſaid Juſtices, the</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>of</hi> May, 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant ſaith, that about fifteen or ſixteen yeers ſince, there was an Imp brought to her houſe by one Goodwiſe <hi>Hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree,</hi> which Imp this Examinant entertained, fed it with oatmeale,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:130529:20"/>and ſuckled it on her body, for the ſpace of a yeer and a halfe, or thereabouts, and then loſt it: And this Examinant further ſaith, that about half a yeer ſince, one <hi>Joyce Boanes</hi> (who is now alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed for Witchcraft) brought to this Examinants houſe another Imp, in the likeneſſe of a ſmall Gray bird, which this Examinant received, and carryed it to the houſe of one <hi>Thomas Toakley</hi> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Oſyth,</hi> and put the ſaid Imp into a cranny of the doore of the ſaid <hi>Toakely's</hi> houſe, after which time the ſon of the ſaid <hi>Thomas</hi> languiſhed, and dyed, crying out of this Examinant, that ſhee was his death: And this Examinant further ſaith, that about eight dayes ſince, <hi>Suſan Cock, Margaret Landiſh,</hi> and <hi>Joyce Boands,</hi> (all which ſtand now ſuſpected for Witchcraft) brought to his Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants houſe each of them an Imp, (in all three) to which this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminant added one of her own Imps; and then the ſaid <hi>Joyce Boanes</hi> carryed the ſaid four Imps to the houſe of one <hi>Robert Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> to torment his ſervant, becauſe hee had refuſed to give unto her this Examinant, the ſaid <hi>Suſan Cocks, Margaret Landiſh</hi> and <hi>Joyce Boanes</hi> a few chips: And this Examinant further ſaith, that the ſaid <hi>Robert Turners</hi> ſervant forthwith fell ſick, and oftentimes barked like a Dog: And this Examinant ſaith, that ſhee believeth that the ſaid four Imps were the cauſe of his barking and ſickneſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Joyce</hi> the wife of <hi>William Boanes,
<note place="margin">Executed at <hi>Chelmesford.</hi>
                  </note> taken before the ſaid Juſtices,</hi> May 6. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant ſaith, that about thirteen yeers ſince, ſhee had two Imps which came into the bed to her in the likeneſſe of Mouſes, and that they ſucked on this Examinants body; and that afterwards this Examinant employed and ſent the ſaid Imps to a Farm houſe in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Oſyth,</hi> called <hi>Cocket-wick,</hi> where one <hi>Richard Welth</hi> then lived, where the ſaid Imps killed ten or twelve Lambs of the ſaid <hi>Richards:</hi> And this Examinant ſaith further, that a little while after, ſhee ſent her ſaid two Imps to the houſe of one <hi>Thomas Clynch,</hi> where they killed a Calf, a Sheep and a Lamb: And this Examinant alſo ſaith, that ſhee carried one of her ſaid Imps, called <hi>Rug,</hi> to the houſe of the ſaid <hi>Roſe Hallybread;</hi> and that her ſaid Imp <hi>Rug,</hi> with three Imps of the ſaid <hi>Roſe Hallybread,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:130529:20"/>Suſen Cock,</hi> and <hi>Margaret Landiſh,</hi> each of them ſending out, were carried by this Examinant from the houſe of the ſaid <hi>Roſe Hallybread,</hi> to the houſe of the ſaid <hi>Robert Turner</hi> to kill the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of the ſaid <hi>Robert;</hi> whereupon his ſaid ſervant hath often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times crowed like a Cock, barked like a Dogge, ſung tunes, and groaned: And this Examinant ſaith, that her ſaid Imp made the ſaid ſervant to barke like a Dog; the Imp of the ſaid <hi>Roſe Hally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread</hi> inforced him to ſing ſundry tunes in his great extremity of paines; the Imp of the ſaid <hi>Suſin Cock,</hi> compelled him to crow like a Cock; and the Imp of <hi>Margaret Landiſh</hi> made him groan in ſuch an extraordinary manner.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Suſan Cock,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Executed at <hi>Chelmesford.</hi>
               </note> taken before the <hi>ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 6. <hi>day of</hi> May, 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant ſaith, that about three or four yeeres ſince, one <hi>Margery Stoakes,</hi> this Examinants mother, lying upon her death-bed, and this Examinant comming to viſit her, ſhee the ſaid <hi>Margery</hi> deſired this Examinant privately, to give entertainment to two of her Imps, and withall told this Examinant, they would do this Examinant good: And this Examinant ſaith, that the ſame night her ſaid mother dyed, the ſaid two Imps came to her accordingly, and ſucked on he body: And this Examinant ſaith, that one of the ſaid Imps was like a mouſe, and the name of that was <hi>Suſan;</hi> that the other was of a yellow colour, about the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a Cat; and that the name of that Imp was <hi>Beſſe:</hi> And this Examinant ſaith, that ſhe employed her ſaid Imp called <hi>Beſſe,</hi> together with the Imps of the ſaid <hi>Roſe Hallybread, Joyce Boanes,</hi> and <hi>Margaret Landiſh,</hi> each of them one, to the houſe of one <hi>John Spall,</hi> where the ſaid Imps killed ten or twelve Sheep of the ſaid <hi>John Spalls;</hi> and that the cauſe of this Examinants malice was, becauſe ſhe being with childe, deſired to have ſome curds of the ſaid <hi>Spalls</hi> wife, which ſhe refuſed, either to give or ſell to this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminant: And further, this Examinant ſaith, that about a week ſince, ſhe, together with <hi>Joyce Boanes, Roſe Hall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bread,</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet Landiſh</hi> ſent four Imps to the houſe of one <hi>Robert Tuener</hi> (by the ſaid <hi>Joyce Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes</hi>) to torment his ſervant, for that the ſaid
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:130529:21"/>ſervant of the ſaid <hi>Robert Turner</hi> refuſed to give to this Examinant a ſack full of chips: And this Examinant further ſaith, that ſhe, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the ſaid <hi>Margaret Landiſh,</hi> ſent her Impe to the houſe of one <hi>Thomas Mannock</hi> in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Oſyth</hi> aforeſaid, where their ſaid Impes killed ſix or ſeven ſhoots or hogges of the ſaid M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Mannock;</hi> and that the occaſion of offence was, becauſe the wife of the ſaid M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Mannock</hi> refuſed to give to this Examinant ſuch reliefe as ſhee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, telling this Examinant, that ſhee was a young woman, and able to worke for her living.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Margaret Landiſhe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Executed at <hi>Chelmesford.</hi>
               </note> taken before <hi>the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>day of</hi> May. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant ſaith, That about eight or nine weekes ſince lying ſicke by the fire ſide in her owne houſe, ſomething came up to her body, and ſucked on her privie parts, and much pained and tormented her: And this Examinant ſaith, that if it were an Impe that came and ſucked her as aforeſaid, that the ſaid <hi>Suſan Cock</hi> ſent it to her: And this Examinant denieth, that ever ſhee joyned with the ſaid <hi>Joyce Boanes, Roſe Hallibread,</hi> and <hi>Suſan Cock,</hi> in the tormenting of the ſervant of the ſaid <hi>Robert Turner,</hi> &amp; doth utterly deny the ſending of any Impe to deſtroy or kill the hogges of the ſaid M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Mannock,</hi> as the ſaid <hi>Suſan Cock</hi> hath charged her withall in the Examination of the ſaid <hi>Suſan.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Rebecca Jones</hi> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Oſyth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Executed at <hi>Chelmesford,</hi> and the firſt that was ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned.</note> taken <hi>before the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>of</hi> May. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant ſaith, That about 24. or 25 yeares ſince, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with one <hi>John Biſhop,</hi> of <hi>Much-Clacton</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex</hi> as his ſervant, there came one morning one to the doore of the ſaid <hi>John Biſhop</hi> and knocked, and that this Examinant go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the dore, ſhee ſaw there a very handſome young man (as ſhee then thought) but now ſhee thinkes it was the Devill; who asked this Examinant how ſhee did, and deſired to ſee her left Wriſt, which ſhee ſhewed unto him: and that he then tooke a pin
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:130529:21"/>from this Examinants owne ſleeve, and pricked her wriſt twice, and there came out a drop of bloud, which he took off with the top of his finger, and ſo departed. And this Examinant ſaith, that about a quarter of a yeare after, as ſhee was going to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Oſyth,</hi> (where this Examinant doth now dwell) to ſell her ſaid Maſters butter, a man met with her, being in a ragged ſute, and having ſuch great eyes, that this Examinant was much afraid of him; who came to this Examinant, and gave her three things like to Mouſes, having foure feete apiece, but without tayles, and of a blacke colour, and bid this Examinant nurſe the ſaid three things, untill he did deſire them againe; And this Examinant asked the ſaid man, what ſhe ſhould give them to eate, and he told this Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant milke, and that they would not hurt her, and wiſhed her not to be afraid of them; And the ſaid man told this Examinant, that thoſe three things which he gave her, would avenge her on her enemies, and bid her murther ſome, but not too many, and he would forgive her; and then went away from this Examinant: And this Examinant ſaith, that the firſt time ſhee imployed any of the ſaid things, ſhee ſent one of them to kill a Sowe of one <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min Howes</hi> of <hi>Little-Clacton</hi> in the County aforeſaid; and the ſaid Sowe was killed by the ſaid Impe accordingly: And this Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſaith, that the names of her three Impes were <hi>Margaret, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,</hi> and <hi>Suſan:</hi> And that a while after, this Examinant and one <hi>Joyce Boanes</hi> (now in priſon) did ſend each of them an Impe to kill one <hi>Thomas Bumſtead</hi> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Oſyth</hi> aforeſaid, who died about three weekes after. And this Examinant ſaith, that ſhee beleeveth that the ſaid two Impes did kill the ſaid <hi>Thomas Bumſtead;</hi> and the Impes name which this Examinant ſent to deſtroy the ſaid <hi>Bum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead</hi> was <hi>Margaret:</hi> And that the Impe which the ſaid <hi>Joyce Boanes</hi> ſent was a dund one like unto a Mouſe. And this Examinant ſaith, that ſhee did ſend another of her Impes called <hi>Amie,</hi> to the ſaid <hi>Bumſteads</hi> houſe, which did kill the wife of the ſaid <hi>Bumſtead</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a ſhort time after: And this Examinant confeſſeth, that the cauſe of offence ſhee tooke ſo to deſtroy and kill the ſaid <hi>Bumſtead</hi> and his wife, was becauſe the ſaid <hi>Thomas Bumſtead</hi> did beate the ſonne of this Examinant for eating up of ſome honey which he found about the houſe of the ſaid <hi>Thomas Bumſtead.</hi> And this Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant further confeſſeth, that ſhee did ſend her other third Impe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:130529:22"/>called <hi>Suſan,</hi> to afflict the childe of one Miſtris <hi>Darcy</hi> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Oſyth</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid: But did withall bid the ſaid Impe it ſhould not hurt the ſaid child too much, and come away againe: And this Examinant ſaith, that the ſaid Imp is come againe from the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> childe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Johan Cooper,</hi> widow, taken <hi>before the ſaid Juſtices,</hi> May 9. 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant ſaith,
<note place="margin">Died in the Gaole.</note> that ſhe hath been a witch about twenty yeers, and hath three Familiars, two like Mouſes, and the third like a Frog: The names of the two like Mouſes, are <hi>Jack,</hi> and the other <hi>Prickeare,</hi> and the name of the third like a Frog, is <hi>Frog:</hi> And this Examinant ſaith, that ſhe ſent one of her ſaid Imps to kill a child of one <hi>Thomas Woodward,</hi> which her ſaid Imp did kill within a fortnight after: And this Examinant ſaith, that ſhee did ſend her ſaid Imp called <hi>Frog,</hi> to kill two of <hi>John Cartwrights</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, of <hi>Much-Holland</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex</hi> aforeſaid, which ſaid Imp did kill the ſaid two children within a fortnight or three weeks after: And this Examinant ſaith further, that at another time ſhee ſent her ſaid Imp <hi>Frog,</hi> to deſtroy the wife of one <hi>George Parby</hi> of <hi>Much-Holland</hi> aforeſaid, which did kill her within three dayes after.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Anne Cate,</hi> alias <hi>Maidenhead,</hi> of Much-Holland, <hi>in the County aforeſaid, taken before the ſaid Juſtices the</hi> 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>day of</hi> May, 1645.</head>
            <p>THis Examinant ſaith,
<note place="margin">Executed at <hi>Chelmesford.</hi>
               </note> that ſhe hath four Familiars, which ſhee had from her mother, about two and twenty yeeres ſince; and that the names of the ſaid Imps are <hi>James, Prickeare, Robyn,</hi> and <hi>Sparrow:</hi> and that three of theſe Imps are like Mouſes, and the fourth like a Sparrow, which ſhe called <hi>Sparrow:</hi> And this Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſaith, that to whomſoever ſhee ſent the ſaid Imp called <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</hi> it killed them preſently; and that firſt of all ſhee ſent one of her three Imps like mouſes, to nip the knee of one <hi>Robert Freeman,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:130529:22"/>of <hi>Little-Clacton,</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex</hi> aforeſaid, whom the ſaid Imp did ſo lame, that the ſaid <hi>Robert</hi> dyed on that lameneſſe within half a yeere after: And this Examinant ſaith, that ſhe ſent her ſaid Imp <hi>Prickeare</hi> to kill the daughter of <hi>John Rawlins</hi> of <hi>Much-Holland</hi> aforeſaid, which died accordingly within a ſhort time after; and that ſhee ſent her ſaid Imp <hi>Prickeare</hi> to the houſe of one <hi>John Tillet,</hi> which did ſuddenly kill the ſaid <hi>Tillet:</hi> And this Examinant ſaith, that ſhee ſent her ſaid Imp <hi>Sparrow,</hi> to kill the childe of one <hi>George Parby</hi> of <hi>Much-Holland</hi> aforeſaid, which child the ſaid Imp did preſently kill; and that the offence this Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant took againſt the ſaid <hi>George Parby</hi> to kill his ſaid childe, was, becauſe the wife of the ſaid <hi>Parby</hi> denyed to give this Examinant a pint of Milke: And this Examinant further ſaith, that ſhee ſent her ſaid Imp <hi>Sparrow</hi> to the houſe of <hi>Samuel Ray,</hi> which in a very ſhort time did kill the wife of the ſaid <hi>Samuel;</hi> and that the cauſe of this Examinants malice againſt the ſaid woman was, becauſe ſhee refuſed to pay to this Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant two pence which ſhe challenged to be due to her; And that afterwards her ſaid Imp <hi>Sparrow</hi> killed the ſaid childe of the ſaid <hi>Samuel Ray:</hi> And this Examinant confeſſeth, that as ſoon as ſhee had received the ſaid four Imps from her ſaid mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the ſaid Imps ſpake to this Examinant, and told her, ſhee muſt deny God and Chriſt, which this Examinant did then aſſent unto.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>The teſtimony of Sir <hi>Thomas Bowes,</hi> Knight, which he <hi>ſpake upon the Bench, concerning the aforeſaid</hi> Anne Weſt, <hi>ſhee being then at the Barre upon her tryall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THat a very honeſt man of <hi>Mannintree,</hi>
               <note place="margin">One <hi>Goff</hi> of <hi>Mannintree,</hi> a Glover.</note> whom he knew would not ſpeake an untruth, affirmed unto him, that very early one morning as he paſſed by the ſaid <hi>Anne Weſts</hi> dore, about foure a clock, it being a moon-light night, and perceiving her dore to be open ſo early in the morning, looked into the houſe, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there came three or foure little things in the ſhape of black rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, leaping and skipping about him, who having a good ſtick in his hand, ſtruck at them, thinking to kill them, but could not, but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:130529:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>at laſt caught one of them in his hand, and holding it by the body, of it, he beat the head of it againſt his ſtick, intending to beat out the braines of it; but when he could not kill it that way, he tooke the body of it in one hand, and the head of it in another, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to wring off the head; and as he wrung and ſtretched the neck of it, it came out between his hands like a lock of wooll; yet he would not give over his intended purpoſe, but knowing of a Spring not farre off, he went to drowne it; but ſtill as he went he fell downe, and could not goe but downe he fell againe, ſo that he at laſt crept upon his hands and knees till he came at the water, and holding it faſt in his hand, he put his hand downe into the water up to his elbow, and held it under water a good, ſpace, till he conceived it was drowned, and then letting goe his hand, it ſprung out of the water up into the aire, and ſo vaniſhed away: and then comming backe to the ſaid <hi>Anne Weſts</hi> dore, he ſaw her ſtanding there in her ſmock, and asked her why ſhee did ſet her Impes to moleſt and trouble him? to whom ſhee made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that they were not ſent to trouble him, but were ſent out as Scouts upon another deſigne.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:130529:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
